Finding Aid for Richard I. Ford papers, 1968-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Richard I. Ford papers 1968-2005 1970-1990
Ford, Richard I.
2010192 Aa 2
University of Michigan professor of anthropology; professor of botany; curator of ethnology; and former director of the University of Michigan Museum of Anthropology. Well-known for his innovative research in archaeology, ethnobotany, and paleoethnobotany, as well as a long and distinguished teaching career and dedication to public and professional service.
28 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Material was donated by Richard I. Ford (donor no 9669 ) starting in 2005.
Periodic additions to the collection are expected.
Portions of the Ford papers are restricted.
The Ford papers includes restricted material in the following categories:
Client Records (Hopi Case Files -- Boxes 8-11
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 24
Student Academic Records -- Boxes 26
Use of the Hopi records is restricted to authorized individuals until pending legal cases are concluded.
Richard Irving Ford was born in Harrisburg, Pennsylvania on June 27, 1941, and raised in Livingston, New Jersey. He earned his bachelor's degree with high honors in anthropology from Oberlin College in 1963. Ford then attended the University of Michigan for graduate work in anthropology (MA, 1965, PhD, 1968), where he worked with influential American anthropologist James B. Griffin, and studied ethnobotany under the guidance of distinguished ethnobotanist Volney H. Jones.
Ford began his academic career as an assistant professor at the University of Cincinnati (1967-1968). Following his work there, Ford embarked upon a long and distinguished career at the University of Michigan in the anthropology and botany departments, where he worked from 1969 until his retirement in 2007. Ford began his career at Michigan as an assistant professor, was promoted to associate professor in 1972, and earned the rank of full professor in 1977. In addition to his dual teaching appointments, Ford served as a faculty associate at the Institute for the Humanities and the Institute for Social Research at the University of Michigan. Over the course of his career, Ford also served as a visiting professor at numerous other institutions, including Utah State University (1981); University of Washington (1986); Kunming Institute of Botany in Xishunghanna, China (1987), Southern Methodist University (1987, 1989, 1991, 1993, 1999); and the Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México in Mexico City, Mexico (1994).
At the University of Michigan, Ford worked outside the classroom as the curator of ethnology (1969-1978), assistant director (1972-1975) and director (1975-1983 and 2002-2005) of Michigan's Museum of Anthropology, chair of the Department of Anthropology (1989-1996), and associate dean for research and computing in the College of Literature, Science and the Arts (1987-1989). He also served on the executive committees of the university's Institute for Social Research (1991-1998), the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies (1992-1993), and the Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project (2002-2006).
Ford was a member and office holder in numerous professional societies including the American Anthropological Association; the American Association of the Advancement of Science; the Society for American Archaeology, the Council on Michigan Archaeology; the Council for Museum Anthropology; the Society for Economic Botany, the Society of Ethnobiology; the International Society for Ethnobiology; and the Baca Institute of Ethnobotany. He also engaged in national service as a member of the National Science Foundation's Systematic Research Collections Panel; board member of the Archaeological Conservancy, Inc.; committee member on the National Anthropological Conservation Curriculum Committee for the National Institute for Conservation; advisory board member for the Herb Research Foundation and the American Association of Museum; and grant reviewer for the National Endowment for the Humanities.
Ford's research interests include ethnobotany from an ethnoecological perspective, paleoethnobotany, subsistence patterns, plant management techniques, origins of domesticated plants, prehistoric agricultural systems in Mexico and the Southwest United States, archaeology of the Archaic, and rock art. He engages in applied ethnobotany through work with various Indian Pueblo nations in the Southwest. As one of the preeminent ethnobotanists working today, Ford has contributed significantly to understandings of how native peoples in North American managed and utilized medicines, plants, foods, and cultural symbols.
Ford utilized his research in his work as an expert witness and consultant. He has assisted the Hopi Tribe in its water rights case (1987), served as an expert witness to the Zuni Pueblo in its land dispute (1983-1985), acted as a water rights consultant for the Taos Tribe (1997), and participated in the development of the Native American Graves Protection and Repatriation Act (NAGPRA). In addition, Ford as served on numerous committees and advisory panels including the Education Advisory Committee for the Pueblo; National Science Foundation Advisory Panel, and the Pew Higher Education Roundtable.
In addition to being known as an extraordinary researcher, teacher, and mentor, Ford's many honors include membership in the Sigma Xi Society (1972), American Academy of Arts and Sciences (1996), and Phi Kappa Phi Honor Society (1998). He was named a fellow in the American Association for the Advancement of Science (1969) and in the American Anthropological Association (1969). Ford is the recipient of numerous awards including a Weatherhead Scholar from the School of American Research (1978); the Fryxell Award for Interdisciplinary Research from the Society for American Archaeology (1987), and the Janaki Ammal Medal from the Society of Ethnobiologists in India (1994). Ford's excellence in service, research, and teaching at the University of Michigan is demonstrated in his many university awards including the Distinguished Service Award (1971); Excellence in Education Award (1991, 1992, 1999); Arthur F. Thurnau Professorship for undergraduate teaching (1993-1996); Borman Faculty Award (2000); and as the speaker for the College of Literature, Science and the Arts' Distinguished Senior Faculty Lecture (2004-2005).
Following his retirement from the University of Michigan in 2007, Ford continued his work as a professional anthropologist, teaching ethnobotany and rock art in northern New Mexico, working on behalf of the Pueblos, and enjoying a research associate appointment at the Museum of New Mexico.
The Richard I. Ford Papers document the professional and personal life of one of the country's most prominent paleoethnobotanists, curator and former director of the University of Michigan Museum of Anthropology, and longtime University of Michigan professor of Anthropology and Botany. The records in this collection measure 27 linear feet, and date from 1968 to 2005, with the majority of the records from the period 1970 to 1990. The Ford papers are primarily comprised of correspondence, legal filings and consulting materials, lectures and conference presentations, publications, committee and service records, administrative materials, teaching files, and mixed media. The records are arranged into seven series: Correspondence, Legal Consultations, Professional Service and Activities, Teaching, University of Michigan Museum of Anthropology, Audio-Visual Materials, and Research, Publications, and Projects.
Subjects:
Anthropology.; Ethnobotany.; Ford, Richard I.; Indians of North America--Southwest, New.; Indians of North America--Ethnobotany.; Indians of North America--Food.; Paleoethnobotany.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Anthropology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Museum of Anthropology.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
China--Description and travel.; Ford, Richard I.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series, 1966-2003 (7.5 linear feet), is divided into three subseries: chronological correspondence, Santa Fe correspondence, and student correspondence. The series includes materials from Ford's early teaching and research career, his work as a professor and director of the University of Michigan Museum of Anthropology, his research trips in Santa Fe, and correspondence from students.
  - Chronological Correspondence
    - 1966-1975
      - General (no surname) (Box 1)
      - A
        - General (Box 1)
        - American Antiquity (Box 1)
      - B
        - General (Box 1)
      - C
        - General (Box 1)
        - Carlson, Gustave G. (Box 1)
        - Cutler, Hugh (Box 1)
      - D
        - General (Box 1)
      - E
        - General (Box 1)
        - Elias, Joel (Box 1)
      - F
        - General (Box 1)
        - Ford, Richard I. (Box 1)
      - G
        - General (Box 1)
        - Griffin, James B. (Box 1)
      - H
        - General (Box 1)
      - I
        - General (Box 1)
      - J
        - General (Box 1)
        - Jones, Volney H. (Box 1)
      - K
        - General (Box 1)
      - L
        - General (Box 1)
      - M
        - General (Box 1)
        - Messer, Ellen (Box 1)
      - N
        - General (Box 1)
        - National Science Foundation (Box 1)
      - O
        - General (Box 1)
        - Ortiz, Alfonso (Box 1)
      - P
        - General (Box 1)
        - Publishers (Box 1)
      - R
        - General (Box 1)
      - S
        - General, 2 folders (Box 1)
        - Smithsonian Archives (Box 1)
        - Snow, David H. (Box 1)
        - Struever, Stuart (Box 1)
      - T
        - General (Box 1)
      - U
        - General (Box 1)
      - V
        - General (Box 1)
      - W
        - General, 2 folders (Box 1)
        - Wilmsen, Edwin (Box 1)
        - Wright, Henry T. (Box 1)
      - X, Y, Z
        - General (Box 1)
    - 1975-1991
      - General (no surname) (Box 2)
      - A
        - General, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - B
        - General, 5 folders (Box 2)
        - Beadle, George (Box 2)
        - Bjelland, Alfred (Box 2)
        - Brown, Michael (Box 2)
      - C
        - General, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - D
        - General, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - E (Box 3)
        - General, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - F
        - General, 2 folders (Box 3)
        - Ford, Richard I. (Box 3)
      - G
        - General, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - H
        - General, 2 folders (Box 3)
        - Hegmon, Michelle, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - I
        - General, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - J
        - General (Box 3)
      - K
        - General, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - L
        - General, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - M
        - General, 2 folders (Box 4)
        - McKey, Doyle (Box 4)
        - Merrill, William (Box 4)
        - Miller, Naomi (Box 4)
        - Minnis, Paul, 2 folders (Box 4)
        - Moore, Josselyn (Box 4)
      - N
        - General, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - O
        - General (Box 4)
      - P
        - General, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Q (Box 5)
        - General (Box 5)
      - R
        - General, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - S
        - General, 4 folders (Box 5)
        - Segraves, Barbara (Box 5)
        - Smiley, Kim (Box 5)
        - Spielmann, Katherine (Box 5)
      - T
        - General (Box 5)
        - Troth, Rebecca, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - U
        - General (Box 5)
      - V
        - General (Box 5)
      - W (Box 6)
        - General, 5 folders (Box 6)
      - X, Y, Z
        - General (Box 6)
    - 1992-2003
      - A
        - General (Box 6)
      - B
        - General (Box 6)
      - C
        - General (Box 6)
      - D
        - General (Box 6)
      - E
        - General (Box 6)
      - F
        - General (Box 6)
        - Ford, Richard I. (Box 6)
      - G
        - General (Box 6)
      - H
        - General (Box 6)
      - I
        - General (Box 6)
      - J
        - General (Box 6)
      - K
        - General (Box 6)
      - L
        - General (Box 6)
      - M
        - General (Box 6)
      - N
        - General (Box 6)
      - O
        - General (Box 6)
      - P
        - General (Box 6)
      - R
        - General (Box 6)
      - S
        - General (Box 6)
      - T
        - General (Box 6)
      - W
        - General (Box 6)
      - X, Y, Z
        - General (Box 6)
  - Santa Fe Correspondence
    - 1978-1979, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - 1993, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - 1994 (Box 6)
  - Student Correspondence
    - A
      - General, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - B (Box 7)
      - General (Box 7)
      - Benninghoff, Anne Stevenson (Box 7)
    - C
      - General (Box 7)
    - D
      - General (Box 7)
    - E
      - General (Box 7)
    - F
      - General (Box 7)
    - G
      - General (Box 7)
    - H
      - General (Box 7)
    - I
      - General (Box 7)
    - J
      - General (Box 7)
    - H
      - General (Box 7)
    - I
      - General (Box 7)
    - J
      - General (Box 7)
    - K
      - General (Box 7)
    - L
      - General (Box 7)
    - M
      - General (Box 7)
    - N
      - General (Box 7)
    - O
      - General (Box 7)
    - P
      - General (Box 7)
      - Peschel, Keewaydinoquay (Box 7)
    - R
      - General (Box 7)
    - S
      - General, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - T
      - General (Box 7)
    - U
      - General (Box 7)
    - V
      - General (Box 7)
    - W
      - General (Box 7)
    - X, Y, Z
      - General (Box 7)
- Legal Consultations
  The Legal Consultations series, 1968-1997 (10.5 linear feet), documents Ford's work as a consultant and expert witness in legislation and litigation on Native American foodways, culture, and land use. The series is divided into four subseries: Fikes v. Furst Hopi case files, NAGPRA legislation files, and Zuni case files. These files include correspondence, court filings, interviews, and expert reports. The series also includes records documenting Ford's involvement in the passage of the Native American Graves Protection and Repatriation Act (NAGPRA), and his work on behalf of the Hopi and Zuni Native American groups engaged in litigation.
  - Fikes v. Furst
    - General 1997-1998 (Box 7)
  - Hopi Case Files
    - Administrative Materials (Box 8)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2039 ]
      - Accounting (Box 8)
      - Background Information (Box 8)
      - Consultants and Permission (Box 8)
      - Correspondence (Box 8)
      - Expense Reports (Box 8)
      - Expert Witness Contracts (Box 8)
      - Files Catalogue (Box 8)
      - Hopi Conference (Box 8)
      - Hopi Interviews, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Statement of Claims (Box 8)
    - Reports
      - Corn in the Flow of Life by Kurt F. Anschuetz, 1992 (Box 8)
      - Dating Early Maize in the Eastern United States by Richard I. Ford, 1987 (Box 8)
      - Hopi and their Maize by Kurt F. Anschuetz, 1976 (Box 8)
      - Hopi Crop Diversity and Change by Daniela Soleri and David A. Cleveland (Box 8)
      - The Hopi Indian, with Special Reference to their Cosmology or World View, as Expressed in their Traditions, Religious Beliefs, Practices and Social Organization by Fred Eggan (Box 8)
      - Hopi Uses of Water in the Little Colorado River Watershed, with a Discussion of Early Navajo Settlement and Water Use in the Little Colorado River Valley by Richard I. Ford, with the assistance of Kurt F. Anschuetz, 1989, 11 folders (Box 8)
      - Hopi Use and Development of Water Resources in the Little Colorado River Drainage Basin of Arizona by E. Charles Adams 1989, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Ives Report (Box 9)
      - First, Second, Third Mesa and Moenkopie Livestock Grazing Outside the 1882 Hopi Reservation by Anthony Godfrey, 1988 (Box 9)
      - Range Management Report for the Hopi Indian Reservation by Harmon S. Hodgkinson 1984 (Box 9)
      - Report to the Hopi Tribal Council on the Little Colorado Water Case by Harry R. Sachse 1988 (Box 9)
      - Tyler Report 1988 (Box 9)
      - Walpi Archaeological Project: Synthesis and Interpretation by E. Charles Adams 1982 (Box 9)
    - Museums and Historical Libraries
      - American Museum of Natural History (Box 9)
      - Arizona Historical Foundation (Box 9)
      - Arizona State Museum (Box 9)
      - Bentley Historical Library (Box 9)
      - Field Museum and Newberry Library (Box 9)
      - Heard Museum (Box 9)
      - Museum of the American Indian (Box 9)
      - Museum of New Mexico (Box 9)
      - Museum of Northern Arizona (Box 9)
      - Southwest Museum (Box 9)
    - Research
      - General (Box 9)
      - 1934 Boundary Case Exhibits (Box 9)
      - Hopi Botanical Names (Box 9)
      - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 9)
      - Plant Lists (Box 9)
      - Smithsonian Files
        - Fewkes, J. Walter (Box 9)
        - Hough, Walter (Box 9)
        - Scott, Hugh L. (Box 9)
        - Sullivan, Jeremiah (Box 9)
      - Photographs
        - Kopta Photographs (Box 9)
        - Miscellaneous Photographs, Uroman and Cory (Box 9)
        - Smithsonian Photographs (Box 9)
        - Untitled Photographs (Box 9)
      - Primary and Secondary Sources
        - Literature Summary (Box 9)
        - Hopi Articles and Evaluations (Box 9)
        - Black, Mary E., "Maidens and Mothers: An Analysis of Hopi Corn Metaphor" Ethnology, October 1984 (Box 9)
        - Barber, Edwin A, "Moqui Food-Preparations," American Naturalist, July 1878 (Box 9)
        - Beaglehole, Pearl, "Foods and Their Preparations," Hopi Economic Life, 1937 (Box 9)
        - Beaglehole, Ernest Hopi Hunting and Hunting Ritual, 1936 (Box 9)
        - Beaglehole, Ernest Notes on Hopi Economic Life, 1937 (Box 9)
        - Bowers, George Ballard, "The Original Dry-Farmers of the Southwest," Southern Workman, 1929 (Box 9)
        - Bradfield, Maitland The Changing Pattern of Hopi Agriculture, 1971 (Box 9)
        - Bradfield, Maitland, "Soils of the Oraibi valley, Arizona, in relation to Plant Cover," Plateau, 1971 (Box 9)
        - Bradfield, Maitland, "Hopi Names for certain Common Shrubs and their Ecology" (Box 9)
        - Brown, William L., et al., "Observations on Three Varieties of Hopi Maize," American Journal of Botany, 1952 (Box 9)
        - Bryan, Kirk, "Flood-Water Farming," The Geographical Review, 1929 (Box 9)
      - Primary and Secondary Sources (cont.)
        - Calhoun, James S. The Official Correspondence of James S. Calhoun While Indian Agent at Santa Fe and Superintendent of Indian Affairs in New Mexico, 1915 (Box 9)
        - Carter, George F. "Some Hopi Indian Food Herbs," The Herbalist, 1946 (Box 9)
        - Clemmer, Richard O., "Hopi History, 1940-1970" in Alfonso Ortiz Handbook of North American Indians, 1979 (Box 9)
        - Colton, Harold, "Hopi Deities," Plateau, 1947 (Box 9)
        - Commissioner of Indian Affairs Annual Report, 1851-1907 (Box 9)
        - Cox, Bruce A., "Hopi Trouble Cases," Plateau, 1967 (Box 9)
        - Crane, Leo Indians of the Enchanted Desert, 1929 (Box 9)
        - Curtis, Edward S. The North American Indian, 1922 (Box 9)
        - Day, A.D., et al., "Arizona Indian Corn," Arizona Academy of Science Journal, 1972 (Box 9)
        - Dorsey, George A., "Mishognovi Antelope-Snake Ceremonies," Nature, 1903 (Box 9)
        - Eggan, Fred Social Organization of the Western Pueblos, 1950 (Box 9)
        - Ellinger, Ed, "Hopi Harvest," Arizona Highways, 1957 (Box 9)
        - Ellis, Florence H. The Hopi: Their History and Use of Lands, 1974 (Box 10)
        - Fewkes, J. Walter, "Ancient Pueblo and Mexican Water Symbol," American Anthropologist, 1904 (Box 10)
        - Fewkes, J. Walter, "The Owakulti Altar at Sichomovi Pueblo," American Anthropologist, 1901 (Box 10)
        - Fewkes, J. Walter, "Oraibi in 1890" American Anthropologist, 1922 (Box 10)
        - Fewkes, J. Walter, "Property-right in Eagles among the Hopi," American Anthropologist, 1900 (Box 10)
        - Fewkes, J. Walter, "The Tusayan Rituals," Smithsonian Institution Annual Report, 1895 (Box 10)
        - Fewkes, J. Walter, "Tusayan Snake Ceremonies," Bureau of American Ethnology Annual Report, 1894-1895 (Box 10)
        - Fontana, Bernard L., "The Hopi-Navajo Colony on the Lower Colorado River," Ethnohistory, 1999 (Box 10)
        - Forde, C. Daryll, "Hopi Agriculture and Land Ownership," The Journal of the Royal Anthropological Institute of Great Britain and Ireland, 1931 (Box 10)
        - Gregory, Herbert E., "The Oasis of Tuba, Arizona," Annals of the Association of American Geographers, 1915 (Box 10)
        - Hack, John T., "The Changing Physical Environment of the Hopi Indians of Arizona," Papers of the Peabody Museum of American Archaeology and Ethnology, 1942 (Box 10)
        - Hakett, Bert, "Early History of the Cattle Industry in Arizona," Arizona Historical Review, 1935 (Box 10)
        - Hester, James J ., Early Navajo Migrations and Acculturations in the Southwest, 1962 (Box 10)
        - Hieb, Louis A., "Hopi World View," in Alfonso Ortiz Handbook of North American Indians, 1979 (Box 10)
        - Hough, Walter, "Archeological Field Work in Northeastern Arizona," Smithsonian Institution Annual Report, 1903. (Box 10)
        - Hough, Walter, "The Hopi Indian Collection in the United States National Museum," Proceedings of the United States National Museum, 1919 (Box 10)
        - Hough, Walter, "The Hopi in Relation to their Plant Environment," American Anthropologist, 1897 (Box 10)
        - Hough, Walter, "Sacred Springs in the Southwest," Records of the Past, 1906 (Box 10)
        - Iverson, Peter The Navajo Nation, 1981 (Box 10)
        - James, Harry C. The Hopi Indians, 1956 (Box 10)
        - Jones, Volney H., "The Establishment of the Hopi Reservation, and Some Later Developments Concerning Hopi Lands," Plateau, 1950 (Box 10)
        - Kelly, Lawrence C. The Navajo Indians and Federal Indian Policy, 1968 (Box 10)
        - Kluckhohn, Clyde, "Hopi and Navajo," New Mexico Quarterly, 1933 (Box 10)
        - Langley, Dama, "Rain-Makers of Mishongnovi," Desert Magazine, 1949 (Box 10)
        - Lawrence, Barbara, "Mammals Found at the Awatovi Site," Papers of the Peabody Museum of American Archaeology and Ethnology, 1968 (Box 10)
        - Little, James A. Jacob Hamblin, 1881 (Box 10)
        - Matthews, Washington, "Myths of Gestation and Parturition," American Anthropologist, 1902 (Box 10)
        - McOmie, A.M. Dry-Farming in Arizona, 1918 (Box 10)
        - Mooney, James, "Primitive Breads," The Archaeologist (Box 10)
        - Nequatewa, Edmund, "Some Hopi Recipes for the Preparation of Wild Plant Foods," Plateau, 1943 (Box 10)
        - Nequatewa, Edmund, "How the Hopi Respect the Game Animals," Plateau, 1945 (Box 10)
        - Page, Jake, "Inside the Sacred Hopi Homeland," National Geographic, 1982 (Box 10)
        - Selected Publication on the Hopi
          - 1.1-- 5.78 (Box 10)
          - 5.79 -- 11.16 (Box 11)
  - NAGPRA Legislation Files
    - Correspondence
      - General, 3 folders (Box 12)
      - Department of the Interior (Box 12)
      - Ford, Richard I. (Box 12)
      - Michigan Department of State (Box 12)
      - Native American Rights Fund (Box 12)
      - Society for American Archaeology, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Legislation and Revisions, 5 folders (Box 12)
    - Media
      - Press Clippings, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - "Who Owns the Past?" Documentary (Box 12)
    - Notes (Box 12)
    - Paper Presentations, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - University of Michigan Museum of Archaeology (Box 12)
    - Statements and Reports (Box 12)
  - Zuni Case Files
    - Administrative Materials
      - Accounting (Box 12)
      - Contracts (Box 12)
      - Correspondence (Box 12)
      - Crop Production Planning Meeting (Box 12)
      - Expert Witness Agreement (Box 12)
      - Publications (Box 12)
      - Legislation, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Reports (Box 13)